Register of the Socialist Workers Party records
Hoover Institution Archives
- ADDENDUM, 1929-1998 (Boxes 113-136)
  - Ernest Mandel File, 1947-1996. (Box 128-134)
    - Speeches and writings, 1948-1995. (Box-folder 130-134)
      - “La discussion sur la question syndicale dans le parti bolchevik, 1920-1921,” Quatrième Internationale, 1955 March (Box-folder 130: 7)
      - “The Marxist Theory of Imperialism and Its Critics,”, 1955 August. (Box-folder 130: 8)
        Mimeograph
      - “The Political Revolution in Poland and Hungary,”, 1956 November 30. (Box-folder 130: 9)
        Typescript
      - “The New Reform in Soviet Agriculture,” Fourth International, 1958 Spring (Box-folder 130: 10)
      - “The Industrialization of Backward Countries,” Fourth International, 1958 Autumn (Box-folder 130: 11)
      - “The USSR from the XXth to the XXIst Congress of the CPSU,” Fourth International, 1959 Winter (Box-folder 130: 12)
      - “The Colonial Revolution and the National Bourgeoisie: The Latin American Stalinists in the Footsteps of the Mensheviks,” Fourth International, 1959 Autumn (Box-folder 130: 13)
      - “Marxism as Seen by Bourgeois Economists,” Fourth International, 1959/1960 Winter (Box-folder 130: 14)
      - “Thirty Questions and Answers about the History of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union,” Fourth International, 1960 Summer-Autumn (Box-folder 130: 15)
      - “Khrushchev’s Third Reform of Soviet Agriculture,” Fourth International, 1961 Spring/Summer (Box-folder 130: 16)
      - “L’accumulation socialiste et le taux de croissance économique,” History Nouvelle Revue Marxiste, 1961 November (Box-folder 130: 17)
      - “The New Programme of the CPSU,” Fourth International, 1961/1962 Winter (Box-folder 130: 18)
      - “The World Crisis of Stalinism after the 22nd Congress,” Fourth International, 1962 May/July (Box-folder 130: 19)
      - “The Socialist Parties and the Common Market,” International Socialist Journal, 1964 January/February (Box-folder 130: 20)
      - “After Imperialism?” History New Left Review, 1964 June (Box-folder 130: 21)
      - “The Law of Value in Relation to Self-Management and Investment in the Economy of the Workers States: Some Remarks on the Discussion in Cuba,” Fourth International, 1964 June. (Box-folder 130: 22)
        Printed copies in English and Spanish
      - “A Socialist Strategy for Western Europe,” International Socialist Journal, 1965 August (Box-folder 130: 23)
      - “Trotsky’s Marxism: An Anti-Critique,” New Left Review, 1968 January/February (Box-folder 130: 24)
      - “The Crisis of the International Monetary System,” International Socialist Review, 1969 March/April (Box-folder 130: 25)
      - “Where Is America Going?” New Left Review, 1969 March/April (Box-folder 130: 26)
      - “La place du 9e Congrès Mondial dans l’histoire de la IVe Internationale,” Quatrième Internationale, 1969 July. (Box-folder 130: 27)
        Printed copy and typed English translation
      - “On Workers Democracy” (leaflet reprint), 1969 (Box-folder 130: 28)
      - “Lenin’s Heritage,” Intercontinental Press, 1970 April 20 (Box-folder 131: 1)
      - “World Revolution Today: Trotskyism or Stalinism?” International Socialist Review, 1970 June (Box-folder 131: 2)
      - “Althusser Corrects Marx,” International Socialist Review, 1970 July/August (Box-folder 131: 3)
      - “The Mystifications of State Capitalism,” International, 1970 September/October. (Box-folder 131: 4)
        Mimeographed excerpts
      - “La orientación estrategica de los revolucionarios en América Latina” (with Martin Knoeller; draft Fourth International resolution), 1970 December 1. (Box-folder 131: 5)
      - “The Leninist Theory of Organization: Its Relevance for Today,” International Socialist Review, 1970 December (Box-folder 131: 6)
      - Europe versus America? Contradictions of Imperialism, 1970 (Box-folder 131: 7)
        Printed introduction and excerpts
      - Revolutionary Strategy in the Imperialist Countries: The Speech Nixon and Mitchell Tried to Ban (pamphlet), 1970 (Box-folder 131: 8)
      - “Imperialismo y burguesia nacional en America Latina,” Cuarta Internacional, 1971 February. (Box-folder 131: 9)
        Printed copy and printed English translation
      - “Ernest Mandel antwortet dem Westberliner Senat,” Permanente Revolution, 1972 February (Box-folder 131: 10)
      - “Nationalism and Class Struggle,” International Socialist Review, 1972 March (Box-folder 131: 11)
      - “The Soviet Economy Today: Toward Capitalism or Socialism?” International Socialist Review, 1972 June (Box-folder 131: 12)
      - Construire le parti révolutionnaire (pamphlet), 1972 (Box-folder 131: 13)
      - “Agricultural Revolution and Industrial Revolution,” International Socialist Review, 1973 February (Box-folder 131: 14)
      - “Pour introduire le débat sur la social-democratie à la réunion des BPe européens,”, 1973 March 17/18. (Box-folder 131: 15)
        Typescript and typed English translation
      - “In Defence of Leninism: In Defence of the Fourth International,” Socialist Workers Party International Internal Discussion Bulletin, 1973 April (Box-folder 131: 16)
      - “Workers Control and Workers Councils” and reply to Geoff Hodgson, International, 1973 Spring (Box-folder 131: 17)
      - “Morrow on Spain,” International, 1974 Summer (Box-folder 131: 18)
      - “Ten Theses on the Social and Economic Laws Governing the Society Transitional between Capitalism and Socialism” and “Some Comments on H. Ticktin’s ‘Towards a Political Economy of the USSR,’” Critique, 1974 (Box-folder 131: 19)
      - “Self-Management: Dangers and Possibilities,” International, 1975 Winter/Spring (Box-folder 131: 20)
      - “Liebman and Leninism,” Socialist Register, 1975 (Box-folder 131: 21)
      - “Significado del cogobierno en las universidades,” (Folleto Bandera Socialista bulletin), 1975? (Box-folder 131: 22)
      - Speech on Fourth International history, International Marxist Group Cadre School (Great Britain), 1976 March 7. (Box-folder 131: 23)
        Typed transcript
      - “On the Current Stage of World Revolution,” Inprecor, 1976 June 10 (Box-folder 131: 24)
      - “The Crisis of West European Capitalism,” Intercontinental Press, 1976 July 12 (Box-folder 131: 25)
      - “East Berlin Conference: New Stage in the Crisis of Stalinism,” Inprecor, 1976 July 22 (Box-folder 131: 26)
      - “Mao Is Dead,” Rouge, 1976 September 10. (Box-folder 131: 27)
      - “Sin ‘libertades’ no hay pacto social” (interview), Mundo, 1976 October 23 (Box-folder 131: 28)
      - “A Political Interview,” New Left Review, 1976/1977 (Box-folder 131: 29)
      - “Three Facets of ‘Euro-Communism,’” Inprecor, 1977 April 28 (Box-folder 132: 1)
      - “Comment” on Raya Dunayevskaya, “Leon Trotsky as Man and Theoretician,” Studies in Comparative Communism, 1977 Spring/Summer (Box-folder 132: 2)
      - “The World Revolution, from Its Empirical Phase to Its Conscious Phase,” “The Place of the Ninth World Congress in the History of the Fourth International,” and “Revolutionary Strategy in Europe,” Socialist Workers Party Internal Information Bulletin, 1977 June (Box-folder 132: 3)
      - “A Powerful Case against Bureaucratism,” Inprecor, 1977 September 29 (Box-folder 132: 4)
      - Interview by Rodolphe Prager, 1977 November. (Box-folder 132: 5)
        Typed transcripts of excerpts in French and English
      - “En defensa de las libertades sindicales” (Liga Comunista Internacionalista bulletin), 1977 (Box-folder 132: 6)
      - “Rosa and German Social Democracy,” International, 1977 (Box-folder 132: 7)
      - “On the Nature of the Soviet State,” New Left Review, 1978 March/April (Box-folder 132: 8)
      - “Si el hambre sigue avanzando…,” Resumen, 1978 April 16 (Box-folder 132: 9)
      - “What Is Democratic Centralism?” Socialist Challenge, 1978 July 8 (Box-folder 132: 10)
      - “La IVe Internationale aujourd’hui,”, 1978 October 12. (Box-folder 132: 11)
        Typescript. Includes typescript of Pierre Frank, “La Quatrième Internationale de 1938 à 1965”; correspondence; and working materials, including Socialist Workers Party 1945 minutes and summary “Review of Our Policy of National Liberation Movements”
      - “’The Future Belongs to the Fourth International,’” Socialist Voice, 1978 October 30 (Box-folder 132: 12)
      - “Un outil indispensable pour la lutte des classes” (interview), Rouge, 1978 November 22 (Box-folder 132: 13)
      - “Actualité du trotskysme” (interview), Critique communiste, 1978 November (Box-folder 132: 14)
      - “La IVe Internationale a quarante ans,” Monde diplomatique, 1978 November (Box-folder 132: 15)
      - “Sobre algunas premisas teóricas del Programa de Transición,” Ideología y sociedad, 1978 November. (Box-folder 132: 16)
      - On Bureaucracy: A Marxist Analysis (pamphlet), 1978 (Box-folder 132: 17)
        Printed copy and printed Serbo-Croatian translation
      - “Fatalism as an Alternative?” Critique, 1978/1979 (Box-folder 132: 18)
      - “Why the Soviet Bureaucracy Is Not a New Ruling Class,” Monthly Review, 1979 July/August (Box-folder 132: 19)
      - “On Our Alleged ‘Theory of Bureaucracy,’” 1979 November 1., Typescript (Box-folder 132: 20)
      - “Croissance économique et luttes de classe,” Critique communiste, 1979 (Box-folder 132: 21)
      - “A Critique of Eurocommunism,” Marxist Perspectives, 1979/1980 Winter (Box-folder 132: 22)
      - “Nos divergences avec le ‘comité paritaire’ et sa ‘conférence ouverte,’” Quatrième Internationale, 1980 (Box-folder 133: 1)
      - “La crise économique en Chine,” Inprecor, 1981 February 16 (Box-folder 133: 2)
      - “Marx and the Crisis,” International, 1982 January (Box-folder 133: 3)
      - “Mandel on Althusser,” Against the Current, 1982 Spring (Box-folder 133: 4)
      - “The Need for a Revolutionary International” (with John Ross), International Marxist Review, 1982 Spring (Box-folder 133: 5)
      - “Poland and the Bureaucracy,” International Marxist Review, 1982 Spring (Box-folder 133: 6)
      - “The Threat of War and the Struggle for Socialism,” International Viewpoint, 1982 September 20 (Box-folder 133: 7)
      - “World Monetary Crisis,” International, 1982 November/December (Box-folder 133: 8)
      - Preface to Chinese edition of Late Capitalism, 1982 (Box-folder 133: 9)
      - “Karl Marx, 1818-1883: The Role of the Proletariat,” International, 1983 January/April (Box-folder 133: 10)
      - “The 100 Years of Marxism since Marx,” International Viewpoint, 1983 March 21 (Box-folder 133: 11)
      - “In Defense of Permanent Revolution,” Intercontinental Press, 1983 August 8 (Box-folder 133: 12)
      - “The Role of Information in the Creation of Capital for Multinational Corporations,” speech, Iowa State University, 1983 November 15. (Box-folder 133: 13)
      - “Vanguard Parties,” Mid-American Review of Sociology, 1983 (Box-folder 133: 14)
      - “No Honour among Thieves but They Stick Together,” International Viewpoint, 1984 April 23 (Box-folder 133: 15)
      - “Common Market: The Bosses’ Club,” Socialist Action, 1984 May 18 (Box-folder 133: 16)
      - “The First Six Months of Gorbachov’s Reign,” International Viewpoint, 1985 September 30 (Box-folder 133: 17)
      - “Gorbachov’s Reforms,” International Viewpoint, 1985 October 14 (Box-folder 133: 18)
      - “Marx and Engels on Commodity Production and Bureaucracy,” in Stephen Resnick and Richard Wolff, ed., Rethinking Marxism: Struggles in Marxist Theory, 1985 (Box-folder 133: 19)
      - “Marx, the Present Crisis and the Future of Labour,” Socialist Register, 1985/1986 (Box-folder 133: 20)
      - “The Hundredth Anniversary of Die neue Zeit,” International Viewpoint, 1986 January 13 (Box-folder 133: 21)
      - “Anatomy of a Split: Why the Australian SWP Left the Fourth International,” International Viewpoint, 1986 February 24 (Box-folder 133: 22)
      - “The Social Impact on Europe of the Prolonged Crisis,” International Viewpoint, 1986 April 7 (Box-folder 133: 23)
      - “The Infernal Logic of the Debt Crisis,” International Viewpoint, 1986 May 5 (Box-folder 133: 24)
      - “Chinese Writers Partially Rehabilitate Trotsky,” International Viewpoint, 1986 May 19 (Box-folder 133: 25)
      - “The Role of the Individual in History: The Case of World War Two,” New Left Review, 1986 May/June (Box-folder 133: 26)
      - “’History Advances over Scepticism,’” International Viewpoint, 1986 June 2 (Box-folder 133: 27)
      - “Biggest Demo in Belgian History,” International Viewpoint, 1986 June 16 (Box-folder 133: 28)
      - “The CPSU’s Congress Offers Few Surprises,” International Viewpoint, 1986 June 16 (Box-folder 133: 29)
      - “The USSR in the Mirror of the 27th Congress of the CPSU” (draft Fourth International resolutions), 1986 June. (Box-folder 133: 30)
        Typescripts
      - “What Is the Theory of Permanent Revolution?” International Marxist Review, 1986 Summer (Box-folder 133: 31)
      - “In Defence of Socialist Planning,” New Left Review, 1986 September/October (Box-folder 134: 1)
      - “The Beginning Recession,” International Viewpoint, 1986 October 13 (Box-folder 134: 2)
      - “Building the Party in a Non-Revolutionary Conjuncture” (Fourth International internal report), 1986 October 28-November 1. (Box-folder 134: 3)
      - “Split in the Fourth International and the Hungarian Revolution,” Workers Press, 1986 November 1 (Box-folder 134: 4)
      - The Place of Marxism in History(International Institute for Research and Education pamphlet), 1986 (Box-folder 134: 5)
      - “The Significance of Gorbachov,” International Marxist Review, 1987 Winter (Box-folder 134: 6)
      - “The European Monetary System,” International Viewpoint, 1987 February 9 (Box-folder 134: 7)
      - “Peking’s New Economic Policy,” International Viewpoint, 1987 February 9 (Box-folder 134: 8)
      - “Gorbachev’s Dilemmas,” International Viewpoint, 1987 February 23 (Box-folder 134: 9)
      - “Bureaucratie et production marchande,” Quatrième Internationale, 1987 April (Box-folder 134: 10)
      - “Moves to Rehabilitate the Moscow Trials Defendants,” International Viewpoint, 1987 October 26 (Box-folder 134: 11)
      - Contribution to Naomi Allen and Sarah Lovell, ed., A Tribute to George Breitman: Writer, Organizer, Revolutionary, 1987 (Box-folder 134: 12)
      - “A Historical Victory,” International Viewpoint, 1988 February 22 (Box-folder 134: 13)
      - “New Fundamental Contradictions in the Age of ‘Late Capitalism,’” International Viewpoint, 1988 May 2 (Box-folder 134: 14)
      - “The Myth of Market Socialism,” New Left Review, 1988 May/June (Box-folder 134: 15)
      - “A New Stage of De-Stalinization in the USSR,” International Viewpoint, 1988 June 13 (Box-folder 134: 16)
      - “The Aims and Contradictions of Gorbachev’s Foreign Policy,” International Viewpoint, 1988 July 11 (Box-folder 134: 17)
      - “Glasnost and the Crisis of the Communist Parties,” International Viewpoint, 1989 October 30 (Box-folder 134: 18)
      - “La révolution politique et les dangers qui menacent,” Inprecor, 1989 November 13/26 (Box-folder 134: 19)
      - “Making Revolution: The Rebirth of East German Socialism,” Village Voice, 1989 November 21 (Box-folder 134: 20)
      - “The Future of Communism,” International Viewpoint, 1990 February 26 (Box-folder 134: 21)
      - “Socialism and the Future,” International Viewpoint, 1992 September 14 (Box-folder 134: 22)
      - “The Impasse of Schematic Dogmatism,” International Socialism, 1992 Autumn (Box-folder 134: 23)
      - “’The Capitalists Don’t Know What To Do’” (interview), International Viewpoint, 1995 May 15 (Box-folder 134: 24)
      - “World Socialist Revolution Today,” Bulletin in Defense of Marxism, 1995 May/June (Box-folder 134: 25)
      - “The Luck of a Crazy Youth” (interview), New Left Review, 1995 September/October (Box-folder 134: 26)
      - Reviews of books by Mandel, 1979-1995 (Box-folder 134: 27)
      - Printed articles and miscellaneous printed matter relating to Mandel, 1964-1995 (Box-folder 134: 28)
      - Obituaries and memorial meeting notices, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 134: 29)
  - Socialist Workers Party Leadership School File, 1986 (Box 135-136)
    Syllabus and instructional materials for course on Karl Marx/Friedrich Engels Political Writings
    - Series I. “Rise of Capitalist Mode of Production.” Includes introductory materials (Box-folder 135: 1)
    - Series II. “Engels and Marx’s Early Journalism: The Democrats Become Communists” (Box-folder 135: 2)
    - Series III. “Marx and Engels the Party Builders: The Communists Become Proletarian and Scientific” (Box-folder 135: 3)
    - Series IV. “Revolutions of 1848-1849 Reported by the Neue Rheinische Zeitung, Proletarian Voice of the Democratic Revolution” (Box-folder 135: 4)
    - Series V. “Facing Defeat in Exile: Rearming and Reorganizing Workers Vanguard” (Box-folder 135: 5)
    - Series VI. “Consolidation of Bonapartism: Opening of the Period of the Second Empire” (Box-folder 135: 6)
    - Series VII. “Land, Labor and Slavery: The Civil War in the United States” (Box-folder 135: 7)
    - Series VIII. “The Organization and Growth of the International Working Men’s Association: From the Revolutionary Assault on the Slavocracy to the Defeat of the Second Empire” (Box-folder 136: 1)
    - Series IX: “Post-Commune Reaction, Capitalist Economic Expansion: The Decline of the International Working Men’s Association” (Box-folder 136: 2)